<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="1030 Modem emulation">
  <p>
    Altirra emulates the Atari 1030 Modem with a simulated connection over TCP/IP.
  </p>

  <toc/>

  <h2>Hardware description</h2>
  <p>
    The 1030 Modem connects to the SIO bus of the Atari computer and establishes Bell 103 compatible connections
    at 300 baud over standard phone lines. The device contains built-in downloadable software to provide the
    T: CIO device as well as a primitive ModemLink program for communications.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation levels</h2>
  <p>
    Three levels of 1030 hardware emulation are supported:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>None.</b> In this mode, no hardware emulation is enabled, and a high-level emulation (HLE) T: handler is registered with
        CIO that communicates directly with the emulator. This provides the best performance and works with most
        software. No ModemLink software is available.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Minimal.</b> This mode adds minimal support for emulating the 1030 Modem to
        so that programs which expect to be able to bootstrap from the T: handler from the 1030 will
        still work. The HLE T: handler is still used in this mode; the bootstrap command simply returns
        a stub loader that does nothing, as the T: handler will already be resident.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <b>Full.</b> In this mode, the 1030 Modem hardware is fully emulated, including SIO-level commands.
      Instead of the simulated T: handler, a 6502-based T: handler is bootstrapped from the 850 instead. This
      mode is required if a communication program is being tested for adequate performance, if a custom T:
      handler is used, or if for some reason the HLE T: handler is not able to bootstrap properly. This
      mode also allows ModemLink firmware to be used.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <h2>High-level emulation (HLE) T: handler</h2>
  <p>
    Access to the serial port is provided by means of the CIO T: device. When the hardware emulation mode
    is set to None or Minimal, this is provided by a high-level handler, so this does not result in a reduction of available memory as with the original 1030 T: handler,
    nor is there a need to load the handler from disk.
  </p>

  <h2>6502-based T: handler</h2>
  <p>
    In the Full hardware emulation mode, a standard 6502-based T: handler is used instead. As with the real 850
    hardware, this can be loaded in one of two ways:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Emulated disk boot.</b> If there is no disk in D1:, the 850 responds as D1: instead and "boots" a disk
        that contains the R: handler. This path allows the R: handler to be used with a communication program
        loaded from cartridge or off of cassette tape.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Direct bootstrap.</b> The 850 also exposes commands to allow direct bootstrap of the handler. The standard
        AUTORUN.SYS that comes with DOS 2.5 will automatically attempt this bootstrap, and other DOSes come with
        programs to initiate this bootstrap. The Additions disk contains both a downloader (<tt>BOOT1030.COM</tt>)
        and a disk based version of the Altirra's T: handler (<tt>THND1030.COM</tt>).
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    The 6502-based T: handler is a replacement handler written from scratch, but is designed to be compatible
    with the original 1030 hardware and handler. Like the original 1030's T: handler, this handler relocates
    itself at and raises MEMLO when it loads. The downloadable handler loads at <tt>$1D00</tt> like the original;
    the disk-based version is relocatable.
  </p>

  <h2>Dialing out</h2>
  <p>
    Most of the 1030's commands are emulated, but dialing is only minimally supported. Both pulse and touch dialing
    will work, and the touch dialing mode will even generate DTMF tones, but the actual number dialed is ignored.
    Instead, any attempt to dial will initiate a connection to the dial proxy address in the 1030 device settings.
  </p>
  
  <h2>ModemLink</h2>
  <p>
    Currently Altirra does not have a replacement for the ModemLink software; an attempt to run it will give
    a message to that effect. The actual ModemLink software can be used if bound as firmware in Firmware Images.
    The image is 10,368 bytes and contains the boot sector followed by the combined ModemLink and T: handler
    software.
  </p>
</topic>