<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Additions disk">
  <p>
    For some devices, additional software must be loaded on the computer to make use
    of that device. Altirra comes with an additions disk called <tt>Additions.atr</tt>
    containing additional software
    for use with emulated devices. Some of the drivers can also be used on the real hardware.
  </p>
  <h2>Software on the Additions disk</h2>
  <dl>
    <dt>ALTXEP80.SYS</dt>
    <dd>
      XEP80 Interface Module 80-column E:/S: driver.
    </dd>

    <dt>ALTXEP8F.SYS</dt>
    <dd>
      Fast version of XEP80 driver. The fast driver uses 31.5Kbaud for transmission to the XEP80
      instead of the standard 15.7Kbaud, for better output speed. Note that the XEP80 must be
      powered off and back on again to work at standard speed after using the fast driver.
    </dd>

    <dt>BOOT850.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Downloads R: handler software from an 850 Interface Module, for when it isn't
      already being downloaded by the boot process. In Altirra, this is only
      usable if full SIO emulation is enabled. It will work but do nothing when stub
      loader emulation is enabled.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      <tt>BOOT850.COM</tt> attempts to workaround some shortcomings in the 850 handler
      download process, particularly that the 850 only answers poll requests once. If
      the poll request fails, a special SIO routine is used to download the relocator
      blind without having to know its length.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      The downloader will detect if R: is already installed and avoid installing it
      again.
    </dd>

    <dt>RHND850.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Disk-based version of Altirra's built-in 850 R: handler. This handler is intended
      for use with the 850 emulation but should also work on real 850 hardware.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      Like <tt>BOOT850.COM</tt>, <tt>RHND850.COM</tt> will also avoid installing its
      <tt>R:</tt> handler if one is already installed.
    </dd>

    <dt>BOOT1030.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Downloads T: handler software from a 1030 Modem, for when it isn't
      already being downloaded by the boot process. In Altirra, this is only
      usable if full SIO emulation is enabled. It will work but do nothing when stub
      loader emulation is enabled.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      The downloader will detect if T: is already installed and avoid installing it
      again.
    </dd>

    <dt>THND1030.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Disk-based version of Altirra's built-in 1030 T: handler. This handler
      is intended for use with the 1030 emulation but should also work on real 1030 hardware.
      Unlike the firmware-loaded version, it is relocatable and will leave more memory
      free whenever MEMLO is below $1D00.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      Like <tt>BOOT1030.COM</tt>, <tt>THND1030.COM</tt> will also avoid installing its
      <tt>T:</tt> handler if one is already installed.
    </dd>

     <dt>SX212.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      T: handler for SX212 modem. This handler is intended for use with the SX212
      emulation but should also work on real hardware.
    </dd>

    <dt>ATBASICX.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Disk-based version of Altirra BASIC; requires 48K RAM and no cartridge inserted.
      Will attempt to run AUTORUN.BAS unless a filename is specified on the command
      line.
    </dd>

    <dt>COLORMAP.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Displays color charts for color calibration purposes.
    </dd>
    
    <dt>LOADEXE.COM</dt>
    <dd>
      Triggers loading of a program loaded directly in the emulator when the program load
      mode is set to Type 3 Poll or Deferred. This can be renamed to AUTORUN.SYS to
      automatically trigger the program load once DOS has booted.
    </dd>
  </dl>
</topic>
