<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Pocket Modem">
  <p>
    The Pocket Modem by BOT Engineering is small adapter that connects to the SIO port and
    provides 300 baud modem connectivity. A special proprietary 500 baud mode is also available.
  </p>
  <h2>Setting up the Pocket Modem</h2>
  <h3>Adding the device</h3>
  <p>
    Under <i>System, Devices</i>, add the Pocket Modem under the SIO devices category as a
    child of the Computer node.
  </p>
  <p>
    The Pocket Modem consists of an SIO end plug, which means it must be at the end of the
    SIO device chain. This means that it normally would not be usable at the same time as
    other devices that needed to be at the end, notably cassette tape drives. However, it can be used
    at the end of a chain including disk drives.
  </p>
  <h3>Loading handler software</h3>
  <p>
    Booting off the Pocket Modem is not possible, so handler and terminal software must be
    loaded off disk. This is not provided with the emulator and must be obtained externally.
    The handler typically loads as the <tt>M:</tt> device, which is then used by terminal
    software written in either BASIC or assembly language.
  </p>
  <p>
    There is an unfortunate stability issue with the <tt>M:</tt> driver software provided on
    the Driver Disk and the DOS DUP menu. The driver software loads low in memory
    and hooks several interrupts including the vertical blank interrupt. The area in which
    it loads is also used by DUP, however, so any attempt to load DUP while the <tt>M:</tt>
    driver is present results in a crash. As DOS will automatically attempt to load DUP if
    no cartridge is present, this typically means that a disk which is set up to load
    the <tt>M:</tt> handler on startup will crash on boot if BASIC is not enabled.
  </p>
  <h3>Hardware capabilities</h3>
  <p>
    The Pocket Modem is capable of full-dupliex communications at 110, 210, 300, and 500 baud.
    Pulse dialing is also possible, but not tone dialing. It can detect both carrier and ringing,
    and auto-answer the phone under software control. Unlike with the 850, it does not require
    dropping out of communications in order to check carrier state.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation details</h2>
  <p>
    The baud rate used over the connection is controlled solely by the rate that POKEY shifts
    bits in and out, and the modem itself is never told of the baud rate. This means that the
    user must pre-configure the terminal software beforehand to the baud rate that will be used
    by the other end. As this is inconvenient for emulation, and emulating baud rate mismatches
    is of limited use, Altirra simply automatically changes the baud rate based on the last
    byte transmitted.
  </p>
  <p>
    Any attempt to pulse-dial a number results in the dial address in the modem settings being
    used to establish a connection.
  </p>
</topic>