<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="410/1010 Program Recorder">
  <p>
    The 410 and 1010 Program Recorders were cassette tape drives which recorded Atari programs onto
    standard audio cassette tape.
  </p>
  <h2>Booting a tape</h2>
  <h3>Machine-language programs</h3>
  <p>
    The Atari OS has provisions for booting machine language programs from cassette tape. This
    is done by holding down the Start button while booting the computer. The computer emits one
    buzz to prompt the user to press Play on the cassette tape player and then hit a key,
    after which the computer begins loading from tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    The emulator can automate this if the <i>System / Cassette / Auto-Boot on Startup</i> option
    is enabled; this causes the emulator to both hold down Start and then press the Space Bar.
  </p>
  <h3>BASIC programs</h3>
  <p>
    If the cassette tape has a BASIC program, it cannot be booted via the above procedure. Instead,
    the BASIC interpreter must be started first and then the <tt>CLOAD</tt> command issued. As
    with the ML boot, the computer will buzz once when ready and a key should be pressed after
    the tape player is ready in Play mode.
  </p>
  <h2>Talking tapes</h2>
  <p>
    Atari tapes are recorded in stereo and have an audio track that is piped through the
    computer to the TV set. This means that music and speech can be played while a program
    is loading. Altirra emulates this if you load a suitable tape recording in <tt>.wav</tt>
    format as a cassette tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>NOTE</b>&#xA0; The <tt>.cas</tt> format has no provision for an audio track. Tapes
    loaded in CAS will never have an audio track and resaving a <tt>.wav</tt> tape as CAS
    will drop the audio.
  </p>
  <h2>Tape control</h2>
  <p>
    By default, the emulator rewinds the tape to the beginning and puts the cassette tape
    deck in Play mode on power-up. This is fine for most simple uses, but for more complex
    scenarios, the <i>Tape Control</i> dialog can be used to control the emulated tape recorder.
  </p>
  <div style="text-align: center">
    <img src="pics/tapecontrol.png" />
  </div>
  <p>
    The tape control dialog contains the normal controls of a tape recorder, including
    Stop, Pause, Play, and Record. Seeking controls are slightly different: instead of
    having Rewind and Fast Forward, two buttons allow for seeking to the beginning or
    the end, and intermediate seeking is done either by dragging the position slider or
    clicking on the waveform graph.
  </p>
  <p>
    The waveform graph shows the two channels of the tape. Atari 8-bit tapes are
    stereo and contain an audio track (left channel, red) and data track (right channel, blue).
    The waveform shown for these two tracks makes it easier to find the records on the
    tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>WARNING</b>&#xA0; While the computer can stop or start the cassette tape motor,
    it cannot detect whether the tape drive is moving or whether it is in Play or Record
    mode. Like on a real 410/1010, if you try to load a program with the tape drive in
    Record mode instead of Play mode, the emulator will happily record blank tape over
    the program you are trying to load. Similarly, trying to save a program while the
    tape drive is Stopped or Paused will produce the right sounds but nothing on the tape.
  </p>
  <h2>Other considerations</h2>
  <h3>Minimal leader</h3>
  <p>
    When loading a <tt>.cas</tt> file, Altirra checks if the leader at the beginning of
    the tape is at least 10 seconds and extends it to that amount if needed. The reason
    for this is that the Operating System waits nine seconds after starting the motor
    before trying to read from the cassette tape in order to skip past leader noise.
    Normally this isn't a problem because the OS writes an 18 second leader when it
    records to tape, but it can be an issue if part of the leader was dropped when the
    tape was digitized to an image file.
  </p>
</topic>