<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Full disk drive emulation">
	<p>
		As of Altirra 2.90, full disk drive emulation is now supported, which means that the disk
		drive's controller and firmware is emulated instead of just the behavior of the disk drive.
		This allows for more precise emulation of disk drive behavior, particularly for disk drive
		types that allow custom code to be uploaded.
	</p>
	<h2>Enabling full drive emulation</h2>
	<p>
		Full disk drive emulation is enabled by adding the desired disk drive in the Devices tree.
		Many variants of the Atari 810 and 1050 are supported, as well as the Z80-based Indus GT
		and the 8050-based XF551. Adding one of these devices will replace the regular disk drive
		emulator for D1:. Currently only one full drive emulator can be used at a time.
	</p>
	<p>
		Firmware images are required for any of the full drive emulations to work. These must be
		obtained externally as they are not included with the emulator, nor are replacements
		provided. Firmware images for disk drives are set up in System, Firmware, Firmware Images.
		If the correct firmware is not available, the disk drive controller will fail to boot,
		typically signified by the disk drive motor staying on.
	</p>
	<h2>Empty drive behavior</h2>
	<p>
		A notable difference between normal and full drive emulation is the behavior when no disk
		is mounted. The normal drive emulator automatically turns off the emulated drive when
		the disk is removed, whereas the full drive emulator stays on. This correctly emulates
		what happens when booting the computer with the disk drive turned on but with no disk,
		and some enhanced disk drives even boot the computer from software in the firmware ROM
		in this case. However, as on the real hardware, this also causes the OS to always attempt
		to boot off the disk drive,
		and in particular prevents entry into internal BASIC without booting DOS.
	</p>
  <h2>Power-on delay</h2>
  <p>
    Some disk drives take an abnormally long time to initialize before they are ready to
    accept commands from the computer, as long as several seconds. This is worst for drives
    like the ATR-8000 and Percom RFD-40S1 that have multiple mechanisms to reset on power-up.
    If the computer is
    powered on too quickly after the drives, the computer can time out on the disk commands
    before the drive becomes ready.
  </p>
  <p>
    With real hardware, this is handled by powering on the drives first and then the computer
    instead of both at the same time (i.e. not by a common power strip). In Altirra, this is
    simulated using the Power-on Delay setting. The "Auto" value selects a value appropriate
    for the typical firmware for the drive type selected.
  </p>
  <h2>Limitations</h2>
	<p>
		While full drive emulation is more precise, it is also more expensive performance-wise and
		limits the ability of the emulator to monitor and enhance disk drive operation. The
		following limitations are in effect when using a full drive emulation device:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>
			D1: acceleration is not possible, either with SIOV/PBI patch or burst I/O. However,
			rotational delays can still be disabled (Accurate Sector Timing option disabled).
		</li>
		<li>
			Only disk types actually supported by the physical drive and firmware can be read and
			written. For instance, mounting an enhanced density 130K image in an emulated 810 drive
			will not work, because the 810 is incapable of reading enhanced density disks.
			Non-physical disk image geometries, like 16MB mega-disk images, will not work at all.
		</li>
		<li>
			Booting BASIC programs directly will not work. This is because the emulated drive is
			always turned on, even without a disk, and thus the OS will always attempt to boot
			from D1: instead of running BASIC.
		</li>
		<li>
			The VRWSafe write mode, which allows virtualized writes but blocks formatting, may
			not work because the emulator may not be able to block the drive firmware from doing
			a format. The format will still be virtualized and usually prevented even in the virtual
			image, but the drive firmware may still format and verify all 40 tracks.
		</li>
		<li>
			Drives that use track buffering, such as the Happy 1050 and the Speedy 1050, will perform
			poorly with or possibly even cause read errors when used with virtual folder mounts.
			This is because the track buffering obscures what files DOS is trying to read.
			The virtual folder mount code attempts to accommodate track buffering, but performance
			is very poor and using a track-buffered drive with a folder mount is not recommended.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		In addition, running full drive emulation also exposes all bugs in the original firmware,
		some of which that are rather annoying -- such as drive firmware that takes too long to
		initialize on boot, or is incapable of properly detecting a density change sometimes when
		swapping disks.
	</p>
	<p>
		For these reasons, it is recommended that full disk drive emulation only be used when
		running software that specifically needs it, such as Indus CP/M or an enhanced copy
		program.
	</p>
</topic>