<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="KMK/JŻ IDE 2.0 (IDEPlus 2.0)">
	<p>
		The Black Box is a Parallel Bus Interface (PBI) based device that adds hard disk, serial, and
		parallel printing capabilities.
	</p>
	<h2>Accessing the IDE+2 menu</h2>
	<p>
		To access the IDE+2 menu, hold down Start while pressing Reset. In the emulator, use F2+F5 with default
		key bindings, or use the Hold Keys function to hold down Start before selecting Cold Reset.
	</p>
	<img src="pics/ideplus2-menu.png" />
	<h3>SpartaDOS X cartridge option</h3>
	<p>
		A subtle but documented quirk of the menu is that the <i>SDX cartridge</i> option is not saved and
		always reverts on power-up. Instead, the SDX hardware switch is used to configure the power-up state
		of this option. In the emulator, this switch is configured in the device settings for the IDE+2.
	</p>
	<h3>External cartridge option</h3>
	<p>
		The IDE+2 has a built-in pass-through cartridge port similar to that on a SpartaDOS X cartridge.
		The emulated device has full support for this
		port as provided by a 130XE's ECI or an 800XL's PBI with the additional cartridge port connection,
		and thus the <i>External cartridge</i> setting is fully functional.
	</p>
	<p>
		This setting is not used when the internal SpartaDOS X cartridge is enabled because in that case
		SDX manages the external cartridge: it initializes the external cart, boots SDX as DOS if
		requested by the cart, and then runs the external cart. Some cartridges will allow SDX
		to boot, while others will launch immediately almost as if SDX were not present.
	</p>
	<h3>NVRAM reset issue</h3>
	<p>
		On a real IDE+2, the menu must be exited before resetting or powering off the computer. This is because
		of a design issue with the Real Time Clock (RTC) chip that contains the configuration: the NVRAM must
		be temporarily overwritten by the time to read the clock and the config data written back afterward.
		If this operation is interrupted, the config is corrupted and lost.
	</p>
	<p>
		Since the emulator can be restarted or closed more often, it protects the NVRAM by default to save the
		config data it is still overwritten by clock data at reset or close. This behavior can be disabled in
		device options if accurate behavior is desired. In that case, exiting the menu improperly will corrupt
		the configuration in the same way as on real hardware.
	</p>
</topic>
