<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Multi-I/O (MIO)">
	<p>
		The Multi-I/O (MIO) is a Parallel Bus Interface (PBI) based device that adds hard disk, serial, and
		parallel printing capabilities.
	</p>
	<h2>Setting up the MIO hard drive</h2>
	<p>
		Under System, Devices, add the MIO to the Computer, then select the MIO or the empty
		slot under it and add a hard drive.
	</p>
	<p>
		Next, set up MIO firmware
		in System, Firmware. You must have the MIO firmware to proceed; it is not included with
		the emulator. As of this writing, v1.41 is recommended.
	</p>
	<p>
		The menu for the MIO is entered by holding SELECT while powering on or resetting the computer:
	</p>
	<img src="pics/mio-menu.png" />
	<p>
		The menu sets which OS drives (D1-D8:) are handled the MIO and whether they map to ramdisks or
		to images on the hard drive. Press N to select the desired slot and then T to change the drive
		type. Use ID,LUN 0,0 for the first hard drive, 1,0 for the second, etc. Adjust the parameters
		on the right to locate and set the size of the disk image. Refer to the MIO manual for more details.
	</p>
	<p>
		Note that if you have set up D1:, the computer will attempt to boot from it and crash, which is
		a problem if you haven't initialized the image yet. Solutions are to either swap it to another
		drive slot temporarily or boot off of a Sparta DOS X cartridge.
	</p>
	<h2>Emulation considerations</h2>
	<p>
		Because the MIO can emulate disk drives, it is important to make sure that the emulator doesn't
		interfere with the MIO emulation. In previous versions of the emulator, it was necessary to
		disable the SIO patch for disks or enable SIO override detection to make this work, or else the
		emulator would intercept the disk request before the Black Box firmware could, bypassing the Black
		Box.
	</p>
	<p>
		As of 2.80+, the SIO acceleration mode can be changed from SIOV to PBI, which causes the emulator
		to use a PBI device instead of intercepting the SIOV vector. The emulator's PBI device is at lowest
		priority (ID 7), so it does not interfere with the MIO. This allows accelerated disk access
		for disk drives not handled by the MIO.
	</p>
</topic>
