<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Corvus Disk Interface">
  <p>
    The Corvus Disk Interface is an external hard disk interface that connects to joystick
    ports 3 and 4, and provides access to a 6MB hard disk.
  </p>
  <h2>Setting up the Corvus</h2>
  <h3>Device connections</h3>
  <p>
    The Corvus interface is added through the Devices tree, under the <i>Controller port devices</i>
    category. Underneath it, a hard disk must be added. The hard disk must be at least 6MB in size
    (12240 blocks).
  </p>
  <note>
    Because the Interface uses joystick ports 3 and 4, it can only be used on 400/800 hardware.
  </note>
  <h3>Initializing the Corvus drive</h3>
  <p>
    Before it can be used, the Corvus drive must be initialized first. The Interface has no
    firmware and the SysGen disk that comes with the Corvus drive must be used to initialize
    the drive. Altirra does not include software to do so, but you can use the same utility
    disks that are used with a real Corvus drive.
  </p>
  <p>
    Follow the instructions in the Corvus <i>Atari 800 Disk System Installation Guide</i>, which
    include running <tt>SYSGEN</tt> from the SysGen disk to initialize the disk and
    <tt>WRITBOOT.OBJ</tt> to create a boot disk. The
    SYSGEN utility is a BASIC program, so you must use the BASIC cartridge in addition
    to the utility disks. Since the hardware mode will be 400/800 mode, there will be no
    built-in BASIC and the BASIC cartridge will need to be attached via the Attach Special
    Cartridge sub-menu.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation details</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra emulates a H-series model 6 (6MB) drive. The disk geometry is 306 cylinders,
    2 heads per cylinder, 20 sectors per track, and 512 bytes per sector. The controller
    is emulated but not the controller CPU,
    so it is possible to trash the firmware area and still interact with the drive. For
    this and other reasons, it is not recommended to try using an Altirra-created image
    on a real Corvus.
  </p>
</topic>