<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The Black Box">
	<p>
		The Black Box is a Parallel Bus Interface (PBI) based device that adds hard disk, serial, and
		parallel printing capabilities.
	</p>
	<h2>Setting up the Black Box hard drive</h2>
	<p>
		Under System, Devices, add the Black Box to the Computer, then select the Black Box or the empty
		slot under it and add a hard drive.
	</p>
	<p>
		Next, set up Black Box firmware
		in System, Firmware. You must have the Black Box firmware to proceed; it is not included with
		the emulator. The firmware auto-scan can detect three versions of firmware and as of this writing
		v2.16 is recommended.
	</p>
	<p>
		On a physical Black Box, the menu is entered by pressing the menu button on the device. In the emulator,
		this is done in the menu via System, Console Switches, Black Box: Menu. This will then switch the
		display to the menu:
	</p>
	<img src="pics/blackbox-menu.png" />
	<p>
		Under Port Statuses, set the sector number for the partition table:
	</p>
	<img src="pics/blackbox-ptable.png" />
	<p>
		The starting sector for the partition table can vary, but 1 or 2 is fine. Save, then exit out of
		Port Statuses and then open the Drive Configuration sub-menu:
	</p>
	<img src="pics/blackbox-driveconfig.png" />
	<p>
		This screen allows ranges of sectors on the hard disk to be mapped to the D1-D9: drives seen
		by the OS and by programs. Consult the Black Box documentation for full usage details. For new
		partitions, you'll want to enter a new name in the Name field, the the sector ranges and density,
		then write the partition to the partition table, after which it should show up in the partition
		list for future reuse.
	</p>
	<p>
		The first emulated hard disk has address ID 0, LUN 0 on the SCSI bus, the second has ID 1 LUN 0, etc.
	</p>
	<p>
		Make sure to Save Config before exiting. After doing this, the partition table will be saved on
		the hard disk image and won't need to be re-entered even after restarting.
	</p>
	<p>
		Note that if you have set up D1:, the computer will attempt to boot from it and crash, which is a
		problem if you haven't initialized the image yet. Solutions are to either swap it to another drive
		slot temporarily or boot off of a Sparta DOS X cartridge.
	</p>
	<h2>Emulation considerations</h2>
	<p>
		Because the Black Box can emulate disk drives, it is important to make sure that the emulator doesn't
		interfere with the Black Box emulation. In previous versions of the emulator, it was necessary to
		disable the SIO patch for disks or enable SIO override detection to make this work, or else the
		emulator would intercept the disk request before the Black Box firmware could, bypassing the Black
		Box.
	</p>
	<p>
		As of 2.80+, the SIO acceleration mode can be changed from SIOV to PBI, which causes the emulator
		to use a PBI device instead of intercepting the SIOV vector. The emulator's PBI device is at lowest
		priority (ID 7), so it does not interfere with the Black Box. This allows accelerated disk access
		for disk drives not handled by the Black Box.
	</p>
</topic>
