<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Disk drives">
  <p>
    Floppy disk drives were the most popular and relatively speedy form of disk storage available on the Atari 8-bit computer.
    Altirra emulates three main specific models of floppy disk drive as well as general forms of other enhanced drives.
  </p>
  <toc/>
  <h2>Overview</h2>
  <p>
    Floppy disk drives connect to the serial I/O (SIO) bus and can be daisy-chained to support more than one drive. The first
    drive is accessible in the OS as <tt>D1:</tt>, with subsequent drives being <tt>D2:</tt>, <tt>D3:</tt>, and so on. Two-drive
    configurations are supported by plenty of software programs, and some support up to 15 disk drives.
  </p>
  <h2>Using emulated disk images</h2>
  <h3>Write modes</h3>
  <p>
    Disk images can be mounted on emulated drives with different <i>write modes</i>:
  </p>
  <blockquote><dl>
    <dt>
      Read only (RO)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      No write access allowed, and no changes written back to source image. This is equivalent to placing
      the write protect tab on a physical disk.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      Read/write (R/W)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Write access allowed, with changes written back to the source image. This is equivalent to a physical
      disk with the write enable notch uncovered.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      Virtual read/write (VRW)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Write access allowed, but changes are kept in memory without automatically writing them back to the source.
      This allows temporary modification of disks while keeping source files pristine. Modified disks are shown
      in orange in the Disk Drives dialog and can be written back to image files via the Save command on each drive.
    </dd>
    <dd>
      Newly created disk images
      are automatically mounted in virtual read/write mode as they haven't been associated with an image file yet.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      Virtual read/write safe (VRWSafe)
    </dt>
    <dd>
      Similar to virtual read/write, except that format commands are blocked with a read-only disk error.
      This allows virtualized write access to disks while still blocking writes for programs that attempt
      to format their disk on boot as part of a protection check. Altirra defaults to this mode until changed
      in Options.
    </dd>
  </dl></blockquote>
  <p>
    For disks mounted via drag-and-drop or the Boot Image command, the default mode is set in Options.
    Individual disk drives can also be changed to specific modes via the Disk Drives dialog.
  </p>
  <h3>Temporary disk images</h3>
  <p>
    Sometimes, a disk image that is dropped into the emulator via drag-and-drop will show up as blue in the
    Disk Options dialog. This means that the disk image is a temporary disk image created during the drag-and-drop
    process. Temporary disk images have no associated disk image file and are common when dropping images from
    a compressed archive, such as a .zip file.
  </p>
  <p>
    Note that this does not apply to .zip files opened directly in the emulator, since in that case the emulator
    knows the .zip file that the image came from.
  </p>
  <h3>Virtual folders</h3>
  <p>
    Altirra can also mount folders as virtualized disk images, creating a DOS 2 or SpartaDOS file system from the contents
    of the folder. This is done through the flyout menu button on each drive in the Disk Drives dialog and is
    useful for bringing files into the emulation without having to assemble them into a disk.
    The disk image is dynamic, so it can adapt to live filesystem changes and the mapped files can be larger in
    total than can normally fit on a disk image. A virtual DOS 2 image can have up to 64 files; a virtual
    SpartaDOS image can have unlimited files. Virtual folder images are always read only.
  </p>
  <h3>.ARC archives</h3>
  <p>
    An .ARC archive can be mounted as a disk image. The emulator decompresses the contents of the archive
    and creates a virtual SpartaDOS disk image to hold the contents.
  </p>
  <h2>Hardware emulation modes</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra supports several different emulation modes, selectable through the <i>Disk Drives</i> dialog.
  </p>
  <table class="std">
    <tr>
      <th>Emulation mode</th>
      <th>RPM</th>
      <th>High-speed rate</th>
      <th>Supported densities</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Generic</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>38400 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>810 Disk Drive</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>Not supported</td>
      <td>Single-density only</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1050 Disk Drive</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>Not supported</td>
      <td>Single-density and medium-density only</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>XF551 Disk Drive</td>
      <td>300</td>
      <td>38400 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>US-Doubler</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>52000 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Speedy 1050</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>56000 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Indus GT</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>68000 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Happy Drive</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>52000 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1050 Turbo</td>
      <td>288</td>
      <td>68000 baud</td>
      <td>Any</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  <p>
    The default is <i>Generic</i>, which allows all disk images to be used and enables the popularly supported
    XF551-compatible high speed mode. The emulation mode can be changed to model-specific modes if necessary
    for software that requires a specific drive model for high-speed operation or for testing.
  </p>
  <note>
    While Altirra supports high speed transfer timings for various drives, it doesn't support the extended
    commands for drives other than the 1050 and XF551. In particular, copy protection emulation, firmware
    upload, and track buffering operation commands are not supported.
  </note>
  <h2>Acceleration support</h2>
  <p>
    While the Atari's SIO-based floppy drives were fairly fast for their time, they are slow by
    today's standards, and it isn't always desirable to emulate them at their original speed. Altirra supports
    a few options to speed up disk access.
  </p>
  <h3>SIO patch</h3>
  <p>
    The disk <i>SIO patch</i> option allows the emulator to intercept floppy disk requests at the OS level,
    handling them immediately. This provides near instantaneous access to the emulated floppy disk and the
    fastest disk operation. Altirra's SIO patch is designed to emulate as many behaviors of the standard SIO
    routine as possible and is highly compatible, even with some copy protected disk loaders. The SIO patch
    only handles a subset of disk commands and will punt to the standard OS routine if an unusual command
    is issued.
  </p>
  <p>
    Programs that directly access the disk drive over the SIO bus cannot be accelerated by the SIO patch.
    This is most easily detected by the characteristic <i>beep-beep-beep</i> transfer sound if the disk routine
    leaves the audio channels enabled. High-speed I/O routines frequently bypass SIO, and SpartaDOS X in
    particular is not affected by the SIO patch.
  </p>
  <p>
    The SIO patch can only operate from ROM and will not activate from RAM-based code, even with a jump through
    the SIOV vector at <tt>$E459</tt>. This avoids emulation errors that would be caused by intercepting calls
    at that location when the code there is not actually for the OS SIO routine. However, it also means that
    programs that copy the OS from ROM into RAM disable the acceleration when they do so.
  </p>
  <h3>Burst transfers</h3>
  <p>
    For programs that cannot be accelerated by the SIO patch, Altirra also supports burst transfer mode. In this
    mode, the disk routine accesses the floppy drive over the SIO bus as usual, but once the transfer starts the
    emulator feeds data to the disk routine as fast as it can handle, raising the transfer rate from the standard
    19200 baud to as high as 90000 baud. While not quite as fast as the SIO patch, burst mode still results in
    much faster disk I/O and can work with many programs that the SIO patch cannot.
  </p>
  <p>
    Burst mode can be enabled simultaneously with the SIO patch. When both are enabled, the SIO patch will
    activate if the program uses the standard OS serial routines, and the burst mode will activate otherwise.
  </p>
  <p>
    There are two sub-modes available for burst mode, standard and polled. Standard should be used by default and
    works with disk routines that use interrupt-based transfers; polled mode should be used instead for disk
    routines that poll the serial hardware instead.
  </p>
  <h2>Copy-protected disks</h2>
  <p>
    Some software was released on disks with special disk formats designed to impede copying of the disk. These
    programs can still be run in Altirra if imaged appropriately, but sometimes some disk emulation options
    must be altered for it to load properly.
  </p>
  <h3>Disk image formats</h3>
  <p>
    Most copy protected software must be imaged in the VAPI (ATX) format in order to faithfully capture the disk
    format and allow the copy protection checks to pass. The ProSystem (PRO) format can also work, but is inferior
    to the VAPI format.
  </p>
  <p>
    The ATR, DCM, and XFD formats do not contain disk layout, timing, or error information, and usually cannot
    properly contain a copy protected disk. Therefore, any copy protected software on such a disk image typically
    either has had the protection removed or simply won't work. Rarely, there are copy protection mechanisms
    that will happen to work with the ATR file format due to the way the emulator reconstructs the disk sector
    positioning, but this is not guaranteed to work in future versions.
  </p>
  <h3>Load timing</h3>
  <p>
    Copy protection mechanisms are often sensitive to disk timing and frequently measure sector load latencies
    to determine whether the disk has been copied. Disk acceleration options can therefore prevent copy protected
    disks from booting properly. The burst I/O option is most often the one that causes problems, since it can
    activate with any type of loader; the SIO patch is generally more compatible, but sometimes needs to be
    disabled too.
  </p>
  <p>
    For very sensitive disk loaders, the <i>accurate sector timing</i> option enables the highest level of disk
    timing emulation, where disk sectors are returned by the emulator with the same delays and timing that a real
    disk drive would have. This usually is enough to load any program, but also results in the slowest disk load
    speed as both rotational and seek delays are emulated in real time. When this option is disabled, the emulator attempts to compensate for the accelerated load timing by
    warping the disk position, which allows most software to load at the higher speeds.
  </p>
  <h2>Conflicts</h2>
  <p>
    Floppy disk drives are common enough that conflicts with other hardware are rare, but there are a few cases to watch out for
    in emulation:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>850 Interface Module.</b> The 850 simulates a disk drive to bootstrap its firmware if no disk drive
        exists, but if one does, it must be manually bootstrapped. 850 + disk drive was a common configuration, so
        many DOSes and communication programs have provisions to bootstrap the R: handler after DOS has loaded and
        this is rarely a problem in practice.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Parallel Bus Interface (PBI) drives.</b> Devices on the Parallel Bus can also simulate disk drives
        with appropriate firmware. In Altirra, this is possible if PBI-capable Ultimate1MB firmware is used. On
        real hardware, this can result in the PBI drive shadowing the real drive of the same ID, and this
        is faithfully emulated.
      </p>
      <p>
        However, in emulation specifically, it is also possible for the reverse to happen
        and for the disk drive to shadow the PBI drive if the disk drive SIO patch is enabled. This happens
        because the emulator cannot detect the PBI drive and intercepts the disk request before the PBI
        firmware can handle it. The <i>SIO Override
        Detection</i> option is designed to correct this by having the emulator let the first disk request
        through and disabling acceleration if the PBI firmware handles the request.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</topic>
