<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="MyIDE emulation">
  <toc/>
  <h2>Setting up hardware emulation</h2>
  <p>
    Both the internal and cartridge varieties of the MyIDE interface are supported. To enable MyIDE
    emulation, select System &gt; Hard disk... from the menu, and specify an image file to use for
    the emulated hard drive in the MyIDE section.
  </p>
  <h3>Hard drive capacity</h3>
  <p>
    The capacity of the emulated IDE hard drive is specified in megabytes. Note that the space available
    to the Atari is generally less, since only 128 or 256 bytes per sector are used. This means that
    only one-quarter to one-half of the drive capacity is used. Regardless, the hard drive image file
    always contains the full 512 bytes per sector.
  </p>
  <h3>I/O region</h3>
  <p>
    Two I/O regions can be used for the IDE interface. Select $D5xx as the interface region for a cartridge-based
    interface, and $D1xx for an internal interface.
  </p>
  <h3>Device speed</h3>
  <p>
    The emulated device can run at either slow or fast speed. At fast speed the emulated device responds
    almost immediately to commands, simulating a solid state device. At slow speed, there is additional
    moderate delay in command completion, comparable to average access time for a traditional hard disk.
  </p>
  <h2>Software support</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra does not include software to make use of the emulated IDE drive. You can use the MyIDE firmware
    or software, however. Consult the documentation for the software for full details, but here are some
    starting tips:
  </p>
  <h3>Disk-based driver</h3>
  <p>
    Boot the MyIDE-OS loader disk and wait for the load to complete. Once MyIDE-OS has loaded,
    either use the Open Image... command to swap the disk in D1:, or eject the disk in Disk Images.
    Do not use Cold Reset (Shift+F1), as this will kick out the soft-loaded OS. Use Ctrl+Shift+\ on
    the host keyboard to send Ctrl+Shift+Esc to the emulation, which initiates a soft-cold-reset.
  </p>
  <h3>Flash-based driver</h3>
  <p>
    You will need to convert the cartridge flasher disk image to a cartridge image by mounting
    an empty 1Mbit+IDE cartridge and then booting the flasher disk. Use $D500-D51F
    as the I/O window for the IDE interface.
  </p>
  <h3>Custom OS kernel ROM</h3>
  <p>
    Rename the MyIDE OS image as otheros.rom in the Altirra program directory and switch the firmware
    mode to Other OS. Use $D500-D51F for the external interface or $D1xx for the internal interface.
  </p>
</topic>