<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Options: Firmware">
  <p>
    The firmware options allow selection of the software built into the machine, including the Operating System and BASIC
    interpreter. The name "firmware" refers to the fact that the software is stored in ROM chips, which cannot be modified.
  </p>
  <p>
    Changing the firmware used by the emulated computer will cause the computer to reboot.
  </p>
  
  <toc/>
  
  <h2>Operating System</h2>
  <p>
    The Operating System submenu lists all OS firmware available for use with the emulator, including both built-in
    firmware and any additional firmware image files hooked up to the emulator through the Firmware Images dialog.
    Besides the built-in and recognized firmware images, you can also add other images with customized names, and those
    names will show up in this submenu for selection.
  </p>
  <h3>Autoselect</h3>
  <p>
    Chooses an external firmware image appropriate for the hardware if one is available, otherwise uses an internal
    firmware.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Atari 400/800 OS-B</h3>
  <p>
    The most common operating system for 400/800 computers, and the best for compatibility in that mode. This entry will
    show up if you have added the OS-B firmware to the firmware list. ATARIOSB.ROM will show up as a patched version of this ROM.
  </p>

  <h3>Atari XL/XE OS ver. 2</h3>
  <p>
    The most common operating system for XL/XE computers, and the best for compatibility in that mode. You will have
    this entry if you have added the XL/XE OS firmware to the firmware list. ATARIXL.ROM will show up as this entry.
    Version 4, the XEGS ROM, is a good alternative for this ROM as it has practically the same compatbiility and functionality.
  </p>
  
  <h3>AltirraOS for 400/800 and for XL/XE/XEGS</h3>
  <p>
    These are internal OS ROM replacements for the 400/800 and XL/XE/XEGS computers, respectively, written in pure 6502 code.
    These are used by default if no other firmware is available. They are functionally compatible with the standard Atari OSes and
    have a good compatibility rate, but you may run into software with issues due to depending on OS ROM internals.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Atari 5200 OS</h3>
  <p>
    Selects the Atari 5200 SuperSystem firmware. You will have this entry if ATARI5200.ROM has been hooked up. The 4-port and 2-port
    versions are similar but not the same; the 4-port firmware is more common and more compatible.
  </p>
  <h3>AltirraOS for 5200</h3>
  <p>
    Selects the internal replacement for the 5200 firmware; you can run most 5200 games with this firmware.
  </p>
  
  <h2>BASIC</h2>
  <p>
    The BASIC submenu selects the BASIC interpreter used with the machine. With 400/800 computers, BASIC must be supplied via
    an external cartridge, and so this option selects the image used by the emulator when the BASIC cartridge is attached from
    the special cartridge menu. With XL/XE/XEGS computers, the BASIC interpreter ROM is included in the computer itself and
    switchable under software control, and is selected by this menu.
  </p>
  <h3>Atari BASIC rev. A, B, and C</h3>
  <p>
    Selects one of the three revisions of Atari BASIC. You will have this entry if ATARIBAS.ROM is hooked up. Most software will
    work with any version, but in general Revision A is buggy, revision B is more buggy, and revision C is less buggy.
  </p>
  <h3>Altirra BASIC</h3>
  <p>
    This is the built-in BASIC interpreter. It is source- and binary-compatible with Atari BASIC, has additional commands, and
    generally runs faster. See the <i>Altirra BASIC Reference Manual</i> for details. Some software may not work with Altirra
    BASIC due to dependencies on Atari BASIC internals, most notably disks that have special BASIC boot loaders (that are
    sometimes not so well written).
  </p>
  
  <h2>Firmware options</h2>
  <h3>Internal BASIC (Hold Option on Boot)</h3>
  <p>
    On XL/XE/XEGS computers, BASIC is built into the computer and is enabled by default. The Option key must be held down on
    boot to disable BASIC. A lot of software requires BASIC to be disabled, and holding down Option quickly becomes annoying
    on both emulation and the real hardware. This option determines whether the emulator itself will automatically hold down
    Option on boot to disable BASIC, saving this hassle. The emulator's display will flash Option for a short time to show
    when it is holding down the Option key.
  </p>
  <p>
    In some rare cases, the emulator may hold down Option too long or in a case where it has different meaning. This is most
    often the case with cartridges with special menus or add-on hardware with boot menus. In that case, the Internal BASIC option may need
    to be enabled to prevent the emulator from doing so, even though it won't really enable Internal BASIC.
  </p>
</topic>