<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Options">
  <p>
    Altirra has a number of options that can be used to customize the emulated Atari hardware.
  </p>
  <toc/>
  <h2>View</h2>
  <h3>Filter Mode</h3>
  <p>
    Selects the interpolation mode for the display. Point gives the sharpest display, but can give artifacts depending on the
    scaling factor. Bilinear generates a smoother display. Bicubic generates an even higher quality display, but can be slow on
    some video cards.
  </p>
  <p>
    Filter modes are not available unless a Direct3D 9 video card is available; if Altirra is running in DirectDraw or GDI mode,
    filtering is controlled by the OS or video card driver.
  </p>
  <h3>Stretch Mode</h3>
  <p>
    Controls how the display is stretched to fit the screen. Fit to Window just stretches, regardless of how it distorts; Preserve
    Aspect Ratio attempts to match the aspect ratio that would be seen on a properly adjusted TV set. Square Pixels always assumes
    square pixels instead, which is mostly the same for PAL, but noticeably different for NTSC. Integral Square Pixels is similar,
    but also ensures that the scaling factor is always an integer, which prevents distortion in Point filter mode.
  </p>
  <h3>Overscan Mode</h3>
  <p>
    Selects how much of the display is visible. Normal only shows the maximum visible playfield region; Extended shows additional
    border regions that are visible on some TV sets. Full expands the display to cover the entire video signal, even horizontal
    and vertical blank regions.
  </p>
  <p>
    The Extended PAL Height option enables viewing of additional scan lines above and below the normal picture area. This is only
    useful when running software that explicitly uses a special trick to display more than the 240 scan lines normally allowed
    by ANTIC.
  </p>
  <h3>Vertical Sync</h3>
  <p>Lock the display to the vertical sync period, thus reducing the amount of tearing seen on screen.</p>
  <h3>Show FPS</h3>
  <p>
    Display the current emulator performance in frames per second in the window caption. This can introduce occasional glitching
    into the video output.
  </p>
</topic>