<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="PCLink support">
  <style>
    .atari {
      background-color: #006374;
      color: #5ac9da;
      display: inline-block;
    }

    .atari-inverted {
      background-color: #5ac9da;
      color: #006374;
      white-space: pre;
    }
  </style>
  <p>
    PCLink support allows a guest OS to access files and directories on the host machine through an SIO-based protocol.
  </p>

  <toc/>

  <h2>Overview</h2>
  <p>
    A PCLink device is a device on the serial I/O (SIO) bus that responds to file and directory I/O commands, typically
    a modern computer connected over an SIO2PC style adapter and running a PCLink server program. Unlike traditional
    disk emulation solutions, PCLink works directly at the file I/O layer level, avoiding the limitations of disk
    emulation and allowing full write access. In Altirra's case, the server program is integrated into the emulator
    itself, making it even easier to set up.
  </p>
  <h2>Configuring PCLink</h2>
  <p>
    The menu item System &gt; PCLink is used to configure PCLink support. The base path controls the root directory
    exposed to the guest OS; files and directories within this directory and in subdirectories made available.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <i>Allow write access</i> option controls whether the guest OS is allowed to create or modify any files. If
    disabled, all write operations including file creation, modification, renaming, deletion and directory creation/removal
    are blocked.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <i>SIO patch</i> and burst I/O transfer options under the Disk submenu also apply to PCLink, since the
    transfer mechanism is similar.
  </p>
  
  <h2>Accessing PCLink through CIO</h2>
  <p>
    Accessing the PCLink device requires special OS support; it cannot be accessed through CIO.
    This means that neither BASIC nor Atari DOS can normally access PCLink, and for those the H: device should
    be used instead.
  </p>

  <h2>Accessing PCLink with SpartaDOS X</h2>
  <p>
    To access the PCLink device with SpartaDOS X, you must be using at least version 4.43 and have the PCLINK.SYS
    device from the Toolkit disk.
  </p>
  <h3>Loading PCLINK.SYS</h3>
  <p>
    The PCLINK.SYS driver can be executed directly or loaded via a <tt>DEVICE PCLINK.SYS</tt> statement in
    CONFIG.SYS. When it loads, it should display a message like this:
  </p>
  <blockquote>
    <pre class="atari" xml:space="preserve">
  D1:PCLINK.SYS                         
  PCLink v0.3, dev. 6, SIO id $6F       

  D1:<span class="atari-inverted"> </span>                                  
    </pre>
  </blockquote>
  <p>
    The /S flag can also be specified to the PCLINK.SYS driver to use the OS SIO routine instead of SpartaDOS X's
    SIO routine. This allows the SIO Patch option to work and permits much faster transfers.
  </p>
  <h3>Accessing files through PCLink</h3>
  <p>
    Once loaded, the PCLINK.SYS device exports a PCL: device to SpartaDOS X. Files can be copied from and to the
    device, and programs can be loaded from it.
  </p>
  <h2>Host file mapping</h2>
  <p>
    Since filenames are more restricted in Atari operating systems than on modern OSes, the filenames
    on the host must be mapped using more restricted rules. Whenever possible, files are mapped directly,
    but there are some limitations on the mapping:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Files that are 16MB (16,777,216 bytes) or larger cannot be seen or accessed.</li>
    <li>Files whose names do not fit an 8.3 pattern or use characters other than A-Z, 0-9, or _ are inaccessible.</li>
    <li>Filename mangling is used to avoid collisions with reserved DOS device names, such as <tt>LPT1</tt> or <tt>COM1</tt>. These filenames
      are prefixed with <tt>!</tt> on the host, i.e. <tt>!COM1</tt>.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <h2>SIO protocol</h2>
  <p>
    The PCLink device is accessed through SIO device $6F, using the <a href="#dos2dos">DOS2DOS protocol</a>. Unlike
    a disk image, this protocol exposes the host filesystem using a file and handle based paradigm instead as raw blocks.
    While documenting the whole protocol is beyond the scope of this help, here is a summary:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Three main SIO commands are supported: Put ($50), Read ($52), Status ($53).</li>
    <li>The Put command is used to send command parameters.</li>
    <li>The Read command is used to exchange command data or responses.</li>
    <li>The Status command retrieves error codes and buffer sizes.</li>
    <li>Supported function codes include:
      <ul>
        <li>init</li>
        <li>read</li>
        <li>write</li>
        <li>seek</li>
        <li>get file position</li>
        <li>open file</li>
        <li>close handle</li>
        <li>get file length</li>
        <li>find first file/directory</li>
        <li>find next file/directory</li>
        <li>change attributes</li>
        <li>create directory</li>
        <li>remove directory</li>
        <li>change current directory</li>
        <li>get current directory</li>
        <li>get disk info</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    When the SIO patch is enabled, Altirra accelerates PCLink requests issued through the <tt>SIOV</tt> vector.
  </p>
  <h2>References</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a name="dos2dos" href="http://atariki.krap.pl/index.php/DOS2DOS">DOS2DOS protocol (external site, in Polish)</a>
    </li>
  </ul>
</topic>