<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Profiles">
  <toc/>

  <h2>Overview</h2>
  <p>
    <i>Profiles</i> allow for easy switching between groups of settings without having to switch
    everything manually. An example is keeping computer and 5200 console settings separate, as
    the 5200 needs different controllers and different cartridges. By default, Altirra comes with
    profiles pre-configured for the major computer and console types. Additional profiles can
    also be created by the user.
  </p>

  <h2>How profiles work</h2>
  <p>
    Profiles work by keeping settings attached to the profile. For instance, the 5200 Console
    profile is set to store input settings in the profile, so switching to that
    profile loads 5200-specific settings and any changes made in that mode are kept private
    to the 5200 Console profile. Switching back to the XL/XE Computer profile then unloads
    the 5200-specific input settings, removing the 5200 controllers and replacing them with
    computer-compatible joysticks and paddle settings.
  </p>
  <h3>Settings categories</h3>
  <p>
    Not all settings need to be kept in a profile. The default profiles leave out the Full Screen
    setting and <i>inherit</i> this setting from their parent, which is the Global profile. This
    means that the full screen mode setting is shared between all of the profiles, so switching
    to full screen mode in one profile also changes that setting for the rest.
  </p>
  
  <h2>Switching profiles</h2>
  <p>
    The profiles are accessed in the System | Profiles menu. Selecting a profile switches the
    emulation settings to the ones in that profile. Note that switching between profiles causes
    the emulated computer to reset.
  </p>
  <h3>Temporary profiles</h3>
  <p>
    Also on this menu is an option to use a <i>temporary</i> profile. A temporary profile can
    be modified, but isn't saved. This is useful when you want to experiment with some settings
    based on an existing profile, but don't want to deal with the hassle of manually creating
    a new profile just to prevent the existing one from getting changed. If the changes do turn
    out to be worth keeping, turning the temporary profile option off will allow the changes to
    be saved back to the profile.
  </p>
  
  <h2>Editing profiles</h2>
  <p>
    The Edit Profiles... menu option allows profiles to be created, deleted, and modified.
    To create a new profile, select the parent profile to inherit from, click Add, and type a
    name for the new profile. Then, use Edit Categories to choose which groups of settings to
    store in the profile.
  </p>
  <p>
    Profiles can also be dragged in the tree to re-parent them. This changes the profile to
    inherit settings from a different parent profile.
  </p>
  <h3>Default profiles</h3>
  <p>
    The <i>Set as Default</i> button allows a profile to be tagged as the default for a specific
    computer type. This is used when the emulator needs to switch to a particular computer type
    and needs to find a profile to use for it. As an example, attempting to boot a floppy disk
    image while in 5200 mode will cause the emulator to switch to the default profile for
    the XL/XE computer type.
  </p>
  <h3>Visible and hidden profiles</h3>
  <p>
    The <i>Visible</i> checkbox determines which profiles show up in the Profile menu. Profiles
    without this checkbox set can only be accessed from the Edit Profiles dialog or from the
    command line. This is particularly useful for profiles that are only used when launching
    the emulator from another program.
  </p>
  
  <h2>Using profiles from the command line</h2>
  <p>
    Several command line switches are provided to use profiles when launching the emulator from
    the command line:
  </p>
  <dl>
    <dt>/profile</dt>
    <dd>
      Selects a profile by name. For instance: <tt>/profile:dos2</tt> will select the profile
      called "dos2." Note that the name is case sensitive.
    </dd>
    
    <dt>/defprofile</dt>
    <dd>
      Selects a default profile by computer type. Valid computer types are xl, xegs, 800, 1200xl,
      and 5200. Example: <tt>/defprofile:xegs</tt>.
    </dd>
    
    <dt>/tempprofile</dt>
    <dd>
      Enables temporary profile mode, preventing changes from being saved back to the profile
      unless the Temporary Profile mode is turned back off in the UI. This is useful for a kiosk
      style launch where settings should not be saved. <tt>/tempprofile</tt> does
      not select a profile by itself, so it must be combined with <tt>/profile</tt> or <tt>/defprofile</tt>
      to use a specific profile as the template for the temporary profile.
    </dd>
  </dl>
</topic>