<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="SX212 Modem emulation">
  <p>
    Altirra emulates the Atari SX212 Modem with a simulated connection over TCP/IP.
  </p>

  <toc/>

  <h2>Hardware description</h2>
  <p>
    The SX212 modem is a Hayes-compatible modem that connects to a computer either by the Atari SIO bus
    or an RS-232 serial port connection. It can communicate at either 300 baud or 1200 baud. Unlike the
    1030 modem, it does not contain built-in handler or communications software.
  </p>
  <p>
    When used with an SIO connection, the SX212 modem is designed to be used at the end of the SIO chain,
    as it only has one SIO plug and uses the same bus signals as a cassette tape recorder. Therefore, it
    cannot be used with cassette tape.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation levels</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra's SX212 emulation is for an SIO connection to the modem. Two levels of emulation are supported:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>None.</b> In this mode, no hardware emulation is enabled, and a high-level emulation (HLE) R: handler is registered with
        CIO that communicates directly with the emulator. This provides the best performance and works with most
        software.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Full.</b> In this mode, the SIO protocol for the SX212 modem is emulated. A software handler is
        required to provide the R: device to communicate with the hardware. The Additions disk contains
        such a handler.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <h2>Supported commands</h2>
  <p>
    The SX212 supports the following commands:
  </p>
  <table class="std">
    <tr>
      <th>Command</th>
      <th>Function</th>
    </tr>
    <tr><td>A/</td><td>Repeat last command</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATA</td><td>Set answer mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATB</td><td>Set Bell modulation mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATC</td><td>Set transmit carrier</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATD</td><td>Dial</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATE</td><td>Set echo</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATF</td><td>Set full duplex</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATH</td><td>Set on/off hook</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATI</td><td>Information</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATL</td><td>Speaker loudness</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATM</td><td>Speaker mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATO</td><td>Set originate mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATP</td><td>Set pulse dial mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATQ</td><td>Set quiet mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATR</td><td>Set reverse mode</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATS</td><td>Set or query register</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATT</td><td>Set touch dialing</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATV</td><td>Set verbose reporting</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATX</td><td>Set connect/busy/dialtone reporting</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATY</td><td>Set long space disconnect enable</td></tr>
    <tr><td>ATZ</td><td>Reset modem</td></tr>
  </table>
  <p>
    The escape sequence <tt>+++</tt> is used to escape from online state to command state. It must
    be both preceded and followed by a second of guard time to be recognized.
  </p>
  <p>
    Commands can be sent at either 300 or 1200 baud, and the modem will automatically switch
    speeds to match. (On the real hardware, this is reflected in the high speed (HS) light.)
    Online communication, however, must occur at the baud rate of the connection.
  </p>

  <h2>Dialing out</h2>
  <p>
    Most of the SX212's commands are emulated, but dialing is only minimally supported. Both pulse and touch dialing
    will work, and the touch dialing mode will even generate DTMF tones, but the actual number dialed is ignored.
    Instead, any attempt to dial will initiate a connection to the dial proxy address in the 1030 device settings.
  </p>
</topic>