<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The 400/800 Home Computer">
  <h2>Description</h2>
  <p>
    The 400 and 800 Home Computers were the original computers in the Atari 8-bit computer line.
  </p>
  <h3>Configurations</h3>
  <p>
    The 400 has two distinctive features relative to the 800: a crappy membrane
    keyboard and only 8K or 16K of RAM. Almost nothing runs in 8K, and the majority
    of programs will not run with 16K. Hardware modifications were available to
    expand 400s to 48K to fix this problem.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 800 has an expansion bay in the back containing RAM modules and the
    "personality module" that provides the OS ROM. Different configurations of
    RAM modules can provide various memory configurations from 8K to 48K; the
    48K configuration is the most common and the one expected by most software.
    Certain hardware add-ons add another 4K of RAM to give the less common
    52K configuration.
  </p>
  <p>
    Both the 400/800 have four controller ports, but only the 800 has two cartridge
    ports. The left cartridge port on the 800 is the regular one; the right cartridge
    port is the oddball. A cartridge designed for one port cannot be used in the other
    and very few cartridges were designed for the right port.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation-specific concerns</h2>
  <p>
    Because of the similarity of the 400 and 800, Altirra does not have distinct hardware
    modes for the two; the 400 is emulated by selecting the 800 hardware mode and lowering
    the memory configuration to 8K or 16K. There is only one minor hardware difference
    which is not emulated, which is that a light pen works on all ports on an 800 but
    only port 4 on a 400.
  </p>
  <p>
    The emulator also does not have distinct left and right cartridge ports; instead, the
    'port' used by a cartridge is determined by the cartridge mapper. Cartridge images
    using the .CAR format are pre-marked and automatically detected by the emulator
    as a left cartridge or right cartridge. If both a left and a right cartridge are
    to be used at the same time, the right cartridge should be set as the secondary
    cartridge.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 400/800 do not have internal BASIC and therefore Altirra's default option for
    controlling BASIC via the Option key is inoperative with these systems. Instead,
    BASIC is attached from the cartridge menu, which creates a BASIC cartridge on the fly.
  </p>
</topic>
