<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The 5200 SuperSystem">
  <h2>Description</h2>
  <p>
    The 5200 SuperSystem is a game console that is similar internally to the 400/800 computer
    line, but designed exclusively to run pre-packaged games on cartridges with controller
    input, without a keyboard or writable storage like floppy disks and tape. It shares enough
    hardware internals that games can be ported between the 5200 and the 800 with minor
    difficulty, but the two are not directly compatible with each other.
  </p>
  <h3>Ports</h3>
  <p>
    The 5200 has a cartridge port and either two or four controller ports, depending on the model.
    Both take 5200-specific cartridges and controllers that are incompatible with the 800. There
    are no buttons on the console itself besides a power button; the buttons to start and reset
    games are on the controllers.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 5200 is notorious for its controllers, which are analog but do not have self-centering.
    Besides the stubby analog stick, there are two fire buttons on the side, which are distinct
    and can trigger different actions depending on the game, a 12 button keypad at the bottom,
    and Start/Select/Reset buttons on the top.
  </p>
  <h3>Hardware versions</h3>
  <p>
    The original version of the 5200 had four controller ports, whereas a later version was made
    with only two. There are two additional differences between the consoles, both minor. First,
    the 2-port version contained hardware updates to support the 2600 adaptor, which is not
    applicable to emulation. Second, the 2-port version also came with an updated BIOS ROM to
    support a future PAL version that never shipped. There are a few games which are incompatible with
    the 2-port version of the BIOS as a result of these changes.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation-specific concerns</h2>
  <p>
    Because the 5200 is incompatible with computer peripherals and software, Altirra defaults to
    having a separate configuration profile for 5200 mode. Running a 5200 cartridge will automatically
    switch to this profile, and cartridge and input maps set in this mode will only affect 5200
    operation. This prevents accidentally mixing settings between the two modes and creating
    impossible configurations that don't work.
  </p>
  <p>
    There is no default screen on the 5200, since the 5200 cannot be powered on without a
    cartridge. (The console is designed so that the cartridge is required to complete the
    power circuit, and removing it turns off the power.) In Altirra, a standby cartridge
    is substituted whenever a cartridge is removed. This cartridge also doubles as a controller
    test to check that input mappings are working as expected.
  </p>
  <p>
    Some games use the analog stick for precise positioning, like Missile Command, while others
    use it for less-precise directional control, like Pengo. The emulator cannot tell which control
    style the game prefers, so it comes with defaults to bind the controller both in "absolute"
    and "relative" styles. Absolute positioning maps input directions directly to those same
    directions on the analog stick; relative positioning uses input to nudge the stick in that
    direction. You will need to manually choose the input map that more closely suits the
    control style of each game.
  </p>
</topic>
