<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The 1200XL Home Computers">
  <h2>Description</h2>
  <p>
    The 1200XL was a redesigned and upgraded version of the 800 computer. Despite the numbering
    scheme, it predates the 800XL, which fixed some of the 1200XL's shortcomings.
  </p>
  <h3>Configurations</h3>
  <p>
    Compared to a 48K 800, the 1200XL has 64K of RAM, and an updated 16K OS with built-in
    self test. There is only one cartridge port, with no right cartridge
    support, and only two joystick ports instead of four. It has some unique features
    not found in any other model in the computer line: two software controllable LEDs
    and four F1-F4 function keys.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 1200XL shipped with an updated OS that had some unfortunate incompatibilities
    with the OS-B that was used with the 800. A Translator disk was provided to load
    OS-B into the 1200XL's high RAM, permitting some incompatible programs to run. The
    800XL's updated OS fixed some of the compatibility issues.
  </p>
  <p>
    There is no equivalent to the Parallel Bus Interface (PBI) or Enhanced Cartridge
    Interface (ECI) ports on the 1200XL. The 1200XL also does not have internal BASIC.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation-specific concerns</h2>
  <p>
    The 1200XL is a bit of an odd duck. Usually, it's preferable to emulate an 800XL
    instead of a 1200XL since there was little, if any, software that required a 1200XL.
  </p>
  <p>
    Altirra has both separate hardware modes and default profiles for the 1200XL. The
    function keys are seldom used and not mapped by default; they can be enabled in
    Keyboard Options, replacing the default turbo and console key mappings unless
    remapped. LEDs are displayed at the bottom, if lit.
  </p>
  <p>
    Like the 400/800, the 1200XL does not have internal BASIC, and the BASIC cartridge
    must be attached if desired.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 1200XL's unique OS is required to reproduce the quirks of that system, but
    it can be run with an 800XL OS instead.
  </p>
</topic>
