<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The XE Game System (XEGS)">
  <h2>Description</h2>
  <p>
    The XE Game System, or XEGS, is a mildly adapted version of the 800XL computer intended to
    double both as a game console and a computer. It is much more similar to the computer line
    than the 5200 and the vast majority of software that runs on an 800XL will also run on the
    XEGS.
  </p>
  <h3>Configuration</h3>
  <p>
    The XEGS is very similar internally to the 800XL: 64K of RAM, 16K OS ROM with built-in self
    test, 8K internal BASIC ROM, and the same ANTIC/GTIA/POKEY/PIA chips. It also takes the same
    cartridges and has a serial I/O bus connection for disk drives and other SIO peripherals.
    Thus, it can run the same cartridge programs, BASIC programs, DOS, etc.
  </p>
  <p>
    There are a couple of minor hardware additions. The keyboard is detachable and optional on
    the XEGS, and software can detect if the keyboard is attached. The XEGS also has an additional
    8K internal game ROM containing Missile Command, which activates if the keyboard is detached or
    SELECT is pressed. The OS ROM is also slightly revised over the XL/XE line, with a newer
    version 4 OS that contains support for booting without the keyboard.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation-specific concerns</h2>
  <p>
    Emulating the XEGS in Altirra is nearly the same as emulating an 800XL. By default, the XEGS
    profile has its own hardware and firmware settings, but the majority of settings are shared
    with the rest of the computer line.
  </p>
  <p>
    The keyboard can be "detached" or "attached" in System &gt; Console Switches &gt; Keyboard
    Present (XEGS). For this to work, the version 4 OS must be used, sometimes called <tt>atarixegs.rom</tt>.
    The common version 2 OS ("<tt>atarixl.rom</tt>") can be used if the version 4 OS is not
    available, but detached operation and Missile Command will not activate.
  </p>
  <p>
    The version of Missile Command that ships with the XEGS is modified to work with the XEGS's
    version 4 OS. Some older versions of Missile Command were hardcoded to the 800's OS and will
    break if run on the XEGS; the symptom of a version mismatch is that game's keyboard controls
    won't work and the level parameters can't be changed.
  </p>
</topic>
