<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="The 800XL/130XE Home Computers">
  <h2>Description</h2>
  <p>
    The 800XL and 130XE computers were upgraded versions of the 800 Home Computer.
    600XL and 800XE were minor variants in this line.
  </p>
  <h3>Configurations</h3>
  <p>
    Compared to a 48K 800, the 800XL has 64K of RAM, an updated 16K OS with built-in
    self test, and built-in BASIC. There is only one cartridge port, with no right cartridge
    support, and only two joystick ports instead of four. The 800XL also adds a new port
    on the back called the Parallel Bus Interface (PBI), which adds additional expansion
    capabilities by devices that can directly interface to the CPU bus and was popular
    for hard drive expansions.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 130XE adds another 64K of extended RAM for 128K total. Unlike earlier third-party
    memory expansions, the 130XE has the unique capability of independent CPU and ANTIC
    access enables for the extended RAM. The PBI port was also replaced by the Enhanced
    Cartridge Interface (ECI), which combines the cartridge port with an additional side
    port to form a comparable PBI-like interface.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulation-specific concerns</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra has separate hardware modes for the 800XL and 130XE, but only a common
    default XL/XE profile. It is rare for software to work on one and not the other;
    the extended RAM separate access feature was rarely used, so software that used the
    130XE's extra RAM would usually run on an expanded 800XL. There are also obscure
    minor hardware differences between the two that can cause incompatibilities and
    are toggled between the two hardware modes, but software that is sensitive to those
    is extremely rare.
  </p>
  <p>
    A rather annoying addition to the 800XL was the introduction of the internal BASIC, which
    would not have been an issue except that it defaults to being enabled unless the
    Option key is held on power-up. This does not cause problems for cartridge-based software,
    but a substantial amount of disk-based software will crash if loaded with BASIC
    enabled. For this reason, the emulator has a internal BASIC toggle option that will
    automatically hold the Option key on startup. In rare cases this can cause problems due
    to being interpreted as something other than a request to disable BASIC, so
    the screen will show [Option] briefly on the side to indicate that the Option key
    is being held down automatically by the emulator. Some modified OS ROMs also invert this
    behavior for convenience; these ROMs need to be tagged appropriately when added in
    Firmware Images for the emulator to recognize the flipped behavior and adjust its use
    of the Option button accordingly.
  </p>
  <p>
    While there are some differences in capability between the Parallel Bus Interface (PBI)
    port of the 800XL and the Enhanced Cartridge Interface (ECI) of the 130XE, adapters were
    often available to use the same hardware with both, and the emulator does not make a
    distinction between the two: hardware is added via the Devices tree in the same
    way regardless of whether the emulated system has a PBI or ECI port. This does allow for
    the minor impossibility of using a cartridge together with an ECI device that did not
    originally have a cartridge pass-through, though.
  </p>
</topic>
