<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="General issues">
  <toc/>

  <h2>PAL vs. NTSC</h2>
  <p>
    The 8-bit Atari was originally created for the NTSC standard and later adapted for PAL. As such, much of commercial
    software was designed for NTSC. Productivity software will usually work fine on either setting, but many games will
    only run at their correct speed on NTSC hardware settings. These games will run correctly on PAL, but 16% too
    slowly.
  </p>
  <p>
    Later software is the opposite, as much of the later and more advanced programs and games were developed in Europe
    on PAL hardware. Almost all demos are designed for PAL, as are the very late games that take advantage of expanded
    memory and push the hardware to its limits. These will run too fast or malfunction if run with NTSC timing.
  </p>
  <p>
    Note that while almost all NTSC-designed software will run in PAL, some PAL software may malfunction in NTSC. This
    is usually due to the shorter vertical blank period. Screen corruption at the top of the frame is one common
    symptom, if the program doesn't lock up entirely.
  </p>

  <h2>Memory size</h2>
  <p>
    The typical choices here are 48K, 64K, and 320K. Very little software requires any other setting than these three.
  </p>
  <p>
    48K was the maximum memory configuration for the original Atari 800 and is only possible in that hardware mode,
    as XL computers came with 64K minimum. In Altirra, selecting 48K is synonymous with switching to the 800 hardware
    configuration. This is generally only necessary when dealing with very old software that carelessly changes the
    PORTB register and accidentally swaps out the kernel ROM.
  </p>
  <p>
    64K was the standard configuration for 800XL and 1200XL models. This memory size will support most later commercial
    software.
  </p>
  <p>
    The 320K memory configuration encompasses most of the common expanded memory configurations, including the 128K
    of the 130XE as well as several third-party 256K expansions. This setting will run the majority of software
    making use of expanded memory.
  </p>
</topic>