<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Ultimate1MB emulation">
  <toc/>
  <h2>Basic setup</h2>
  <h3>Hardware description</h3>
  <p>
    Ultimate1MB is a hardware expansion that provides 1MB of memory, flashable
    BIOS/BASIC/GAME slots, SpartaDOS X, real-time clock, and SIDE parallel bus interface
    (PBI) disk emulation facilities.
  </p>
  <p>
    Altirra emulates the U1MB with version 2 of the CPLD firmware, which includes
    PBI support.
  </p>
  <h3>Flashing the firmware</h3>
  <p>
    U1MB has 512KB of flash memory that must be loaded with an image containing
    both a BIOS and an OS. The BIOS is needed to initialize the U1MB hardware prior
    to handing control over to a conventional OS.
  </p>
  <p>
    Altirra does not come with the U1MB firmware, which must be obtained separately.
    However, it does contain a recovery image with a minimal BIOS and OS that can
    be used to run the flasher disk to load the real hardware. Alternatively, if
    the image is available in raw image form it can be bound directly through the
    System | Firmware | ROM images menu item.
  </p>
  <h2>Gotchas</h2>
  <h3>Entering the BIOS menu</h3>
  <p>
    The U1MB BIOS has a menu that is accessed by holding down the Help key while
    powering on or resetting the computer. In Altirra, it is easier to enter
    this mode if the keyboard mode is switched from cooked keys to raw keys.
  </p>
  <h3>Inactive menu items</h3>
  <p>
    When U1MB is enabled, the addressing for VBXE, SoundBoard, and Covox devices
    is controlled by the U1MB mapping hardware and needs to be set through the
    U1MB BIOS. Similarly, the memory sizing modes do not apply when U1MB is enabled as
    the U1MB hardware emulates various memory models under software control.
  </p>
  <h3>PBI disk emulation</h3>
  <p>
    When PBI disk emulation is enabled in the U1MB BIOS, the SIO Patch and
    Fast Boot options should be disabled or the SIO Override Detection mode
    should be turned on. Otherwise, the emulator can intercept disk accesses
    before the PBI BIOS does and prevent the PBI disk emulation from working.
  </p>
  <h3>SIDE SpartaDOS X cartridge</h3>
  <p>
    If a SIDE cartridge is used with U1MB, the SpartaDOS X (SDX) facility on the
    SIDE cartridge should be disabled. The reason is that the SIDE SDX and the
    U1MB SDX mapping registers overlap and this can cause difficulty in
    disabling SDX. A symptom of this conflict is that the PBI BIOS hangs on startup
    because it cannot unmap the SDX cartridge.
  </p>
  <h3>Reflashing the firmware</h3>
  <p>
    Altirra emulates the flash memory in the U1MB, so it is possible to reflash
    the U1MB to newer firmware in the same manner as on the real hardware. However,
    an important caveat that applies equally to the real and emulated hardware is
    that SIDE PBI support should be turned off in the U1MB BIOS prior to running
    the flasher. Otherwise, the flasher will fail by erasing the PBI BIOS
    and then calling into it via a disk read request, resulting in a crash and
    bricking the U1MB. Fortunately, under emulation this is simple to recover from.
  </p>
</topic>