<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Using the emulated computer">
  <toc/>
  <h2>Introduction</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra emulates the behavior of an Atari 8-bit home computer. If you never owned one, you might not know how to operate
    one.
  </p>
  <h2>Powering on - 800</h2>
  <p>
     By default, an Atari 800 computer comes with an operating system in 10K of ROM, 48K of RAM... and not much else.
     If you power it on, you get a tiny program built into the OS called the Memo Pad:
  </p>
  <img src="pics/atari-memopad.png" width="672" height="448"/>
  <p>
    This program lets you... type text on screen. Very exciting.
  </p>
  <h3>The cartridge ports</h3>
  <p>
    One way to get actual useful software onto the Atari was to plug in a cartridge. There were two cartridge ports on the
    800, a left cartridge and a right cartridge. Cartridges had to be made for either the left slot or the right slot, and
    almost all cartridges were left slot (no other model had a right slot). One of the more popular cartridges was the
    BASIC language cartridge, which would give the READY prompt on start:
  </p>
  <img src="pics/atari-basic.png" width="672" height="448" />
  <p>
    The <tt>BYE</tt> command would exit BASIC and start the Memo Pad.
  </p>
  <p>
    In Altirra, you can either attach an image of the BASIC cartridge, or use the Attach Special Cartridge &gt; BASIC menu
    option.
  </p>
  <h3>Disk drives</h3>
  <p>
    With a computer and a BASIC program, you could write and run programs, but not save them for later use. One way to
    do this was a tape drive, if you were very patient. A more useful alternative was the 810 disk drive. This connected to
    the computer via a serial I/O (SIO) cable, and upon power-up, the computer with automatically try to boot from the
    disk. If you didn't have a bootable disk inserted, this resulted:
  </p>
  <img src="pics/atari-booterror.png" width="672" height="448" />
  <p>
    The computer would simply try to boot from the disk drive repeatedly, printing <tt>BOOT ERROR</tt> each time. Note that
    if the BASIC cartridge was inserted, the computer tried to boot from the disk drive <i>before</i> loading BASIC. This
    meant that if you didn't want to boot a disk, you needed to turn off the disk drive. The Disk Drives dialog in Altirra
    has modes to distinguish between a drive that is absent or powered off (Off) and
    a drive that is powered on (R/O, R/W, VirtRW). Two shortcuts to power off drives are to either use the Detach menu
    option, or click the Eject button twice in the Disk Drives dialog.
  </p>
  <p>
    If a bootable disk was inserted, the computer would sound beep-beep-beep as it loaded sectors off the disk. Atari disk
    drives were reasonably fast and took less than a minute to boot DOS. The computer didn't need to make the beep sound,
    but the OS was configured to do so by default and you could tell by the sound whether the computer was reading from
    the disk, writing to the disk, or hitting an error.
  </p>
  <p>
    When booting a disk, what happened afterward depended on what was booted and what cartridge was plugged in.
    Program disks usually booted directly into the application or game on the disk. Others that were based on plain DOS
    and weren't set up to auto-run would go to the DOS menu:
  </p>
  <img src="pics/atari-dos.png" width="672" height="448" />
  <p>
    When the BASIC cartridge was also inserted, DOS would boot and then the computer would enter the BASIC READY prompt.
    The DOS menu could be accessed by typing the <tt>DOS</tt> command.
  </p>
  <h3>System Reset</h3>
  <p>
    One of the keys on the keyboard was labeled System Reset. Its job was to reset the computer back to a sane state in
    case you messed up... usually. For instance, in BASIC, pressing System Reset would stop the running program, clear
    the screen, and display the READY prompt, usually with the BASIC program intact.
  </p>
  <p>
    The System Reset key performed a <i>warm start</i>, meaning that it skipped some of the OS initialization. For instance,
    it preserved user memory, which in the case of BASIC meant the running program. However, it also meant that if you
    needed the full boot-up process, particularly booting a disk, you'd need to power the computer off and on again
    instead of using System Reset.
  </p>
  <h2>The XL/XE series</h2>
  <p>
    The XL/XE series brought some major changes to the 8-bit home computer line. For this case we'll focus on the popular
    800XL and forget about the 1200XL, which is the weirdo of the family.
  </p>
  <p>
    One of the changes is the presence of a built-in self-test, which replaces the not very useful Memo Pad:
  </p>
  <img src="pics/atari-selftest.png" width="672" height="448" />
  <p>
    The self test waits for a bit for the user to select a mode, after which it automatically cycles through the tests
    itself. (The simulated keyboard test was not so useful.)
  </p>
  <p>
    Another change was the presence of a built-in BASIC, instead of requiring a BASIC cartridge to be inserted.
    Annoyingly, this BASIC was enabled by <i>default</i>, unless you held down the Option key when powering on the
    computer. This was a problem because a lot of disk-based software didn't work if you had a cartridge inserted
    and would crash if you forgot to disable BASIC. Altirra automatically holds down the Option key for you when
    requested under System &gt; Firmware, and displays an indicator when it is doing so. This behavior was annoying
    enough that some people modified the OS ROM on their computer specifically to flip the interpretation of the
    Option key on boot.
  </p>
  <p>
    The XL/XE series computers only have two joystick ports, instead of the four of the 400/800 computers, and only have
    a single (left) cartridge port.
  </p>
  <h3>OS compatibility and the Translator</h3>
  <p>
    There were two main revisions of the built-in ROM OS on the 400/800, revision A and revision B. Revision B fixed a couple
    of bugs and was the prevalent OS version. This OS is commonly called OS-B.
  </p>
  <p>
    Atari had defined specific interfaces to use when using the OS, such that sticking to those interfaces would ensure
    compatibility with future versions of the OS. A fair amount of software ignored those guidelines and poked directly
    into the OS, which meant that they failed when Atari created the upgraded 14K OS for the XL/XE line. To run such older
    programs, Atari created the Translator disk, which would load a modified version of OS-B into the extra 14K of RAM
    in the XL/XE computer. You can use the Translator on an emulator, although it's much easier just to emulate a 400/800
    instead.
  </p>
  <p>
    History repeated itself after the release of the XL/XE line, and software was created that would only work correctly
    with the XL/XE OS.
  </p>
  <h2>The XE Game System (XEGS)</h2>
  <p>
    The XEGS was an attempt to make a game console out of an XL/XE computer. Functionally, it was very similar to an 800XL
    with 64K of memory, almost the same OS, and the ability to use the same SIO peripherals, and had nearly 100% compatibility.
    There were a couple of minor differences:
  </p>
  <p>
    First, the XEGS had a game built-in, in addition to BASIC. Holding down the Select key on power-up would
    start Missile Command.
  </p>
  <p>
    Second, the keyboard was detachable, and the XEGS knew if the keyboard was attached. If the keyboard wasn't attached,
    it would flip the meaning of the Select key, so the console would start Missile Command unless the Select key
    was pressed. In Altirra, this can be simulated using the System &gt; Console &gt; Keyboard Attached option.
  </p>
</topic>
