<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Video Board XE">
  <p>
    VideoBoard XE, or VBXE, is an internal expansion that greatly increases the graphics output capabilities
    of an Atari 8-bit computer.
  </p>
  <h2>Overview</h2>
  <p>
    VBXE installs internally within the computer, shadowing the PIA and GTIA chips and producing its own
    video output. It is designed to emulate the original capabilities of the computer well enough that
    the VBXE video output can be used all the time, even when VBXE capabilities are not being used. The
    VBXE graphics hardware is an improvement over the standard hardware in many ways:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>512K of video memory with two independent memory access windows</li>
    <li>640 pixel wide modes</li>
    <li>16-color and 256-color modes</li>
    <li>80-column text mode</li>
    <li>Hardware blitter</li>
    <li>Attribute map</li>
    <li>Extended versions of original ANTIC/GTIA modes, including extended color and overlays</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    VBXE does not occupy any of the regular expansion ports like the cartridge or PBI ports, however,
    so it can coexist with other such expansions.
  </p>
  <h2>VBXE configuration options</h2>
  <p>
    VBXE requires a register memory access window in the parallel bus interface (PBI) space, either
    at <tt>$D6xx</tt> or <tt>$D7xx</tt>. Both options are supported in Altirra. <tt>$D6xx</tt>
    is the more common configuration in real hardware and should be used except in case of conflict;
    most VBXE software is compiled for this address and will not adapt to a <tt>$D7xx</tt> setup.
  </p>
  <p>
    If Ultimate1MB is also active, Altirra automatically routes the VBXE through the U1MB module
    so that it can control the VBXE register configuration. In this case, the VBXE register window
    must be configured through U1MB setup rather than emulator options.
  </p>
  <p>
    The VBXE firmware comes in two forms, a standard version and a "RAMBO" or 'r' version. The 'r'
    version emulates a RAMBO 256K memory expansion. This is supported in Altirra through the <i>Use
    VBXE memory for expansion</i> option, but the memory configuration must be adjusted to match.
  </p>
  <h2>Using VBXE</h2>
  <p>
    VBXE only has device firmware and no computer firmware, so booting a system with VBXE installed
    only has the VBXE emulating the standard display and no new functionality is available. To use
    VBXE extended features, software must be loaded that specifically supports VBXE.
  </p>
  <h2>Emulator limitations</h2>
  <p>
    Because VBXE can produce video with higher color depth and resolution than standard GTIA, some
    emulation options are altered or limited when VBXE is active. Screenshots are captured twice
    as wide, and the high artifacting modes are not available. VBXE emulation is also a bit slower
    than standard GTIA emulation.
  </p>
  <p>
    On a real VBXE, the starting palette is baked into the device firmware itself, and so the color
    adjustment on the Atari has no effect on the VBXE display. In Altirra, the color adjustments
    are reflected in the VBXE's initial palette 0. This can lead to some slight color errors in
    VBXE-based software that relies on the initial color values in the original VBXE firmware. Newer
    revisions of the firmware also allow for adjusted palettes, so it is best that software be able to
    handle this in any case.
  </p>
</topic>
