<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="XEP80 Interface Module">
  <p>
    The XEP80 Interface Module was an 80-column display module that connected to the joystick port of
    the Atari. Altirra emulates all official and some unofficial functionality of the XEP80, but not
    the printer port.
  </p>
  <h2>Usage</h2>
  <p>
    XEP80 emulation is enabled via the System &gt; XEP80 menu and emulates an XEP80 device plugged
    into joystick port 2. For this to work, no other input device should be activated that also uses
    port 2 (this is impossible on real hardware except by soldering or other physical means).
  </p>
  <p>
    Once XEP80 emulation is enabled, display driver software must be loaded to use it.
    You can either use the <tt>XEP80.SYS</tt> included with the original XEP80 software disk, or you can
    use the replacement <tt>ALTXEP80.SYS</tt> from the Additions disk.
  </p>
  <p>
    The XEP80 generates a different display parallel to the one usually created by the Atari.
    In Altirra, use View &gt; XEP80 View to toggle between the standard display and the XEP80 display.
    The Auto-switch XEP80 View option makes this easier by automatically switching to the XEP80's
    display if it receives valid data and back to the standard display on reset.
  </p>
  <h2>Caveats</h2>
  <p>
    The printer interface isn't emulated.
  </p>
  <p>
    Altirra attempts to emulate a fair amount of undocumented behavior within the XEP80, particularly
    with regard to altering the display registers and changing UART baud rates. However, the XEP80
    testing command set allows hardware registers and internal memory to be overwritten in ways that
    can cause very unusual behavior, and not all of that is emulated.
  </p>
  <p>
    Only software specifically designed for the XEP80 or that works through standard CIO E: and S:
    interfaces will work with it. Programs that write directly to the screen buffer or hardware registers
    will not work either in emulation or real hardware. This excludes most games and even some productivity
    software.
  </p>
  <p>
    The actual XEP80 hardware is notorious for extreme amounts of vertical overscan since it generates
    250 active scanlines in NTSC and 300 in PAL in text mode. As such, while the emulator shows all 25
    rows of text, the top and bottom rows are seldom completely visible on real hardware, subject to
    depending on the TV set.
  </p>
  <p>
    It is possible to reprogram the XEP80 for custom horizontal and vertical refresh rates. Altirra
    allows horizontal refresh rates of 14.7-16.7KHz and vertical rates of 48-52Hz (PAL) or 58-62Hz (NTSC).
    Scanning rates that are out of tolerance will result in an unsupported screen mode message similar.
  </p>
</topic>
